The following content is provided
提供以下内容
under a Creative Commons license.
根据知识共享许可。
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue
您的支持将帮助MIT OpenCourseWare继续
to offer high quality educational resources for free.
免费提供高质量的教育资源。
To make a donation or view additional materials
捐款或查看其他材料
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
从数百门麻省理工学院的课程中，访问MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
在ocw.mit.edu。
PROFESSOR: I hope you're all recovered from the quiz.
教授：我希望你们都从测验中康复。
Our apologies for hard questions,
对于一些难题，我们深表歉意，
but it's just the first quiz.
但这只是第一次测验。
We have a lot more fun things to do in 006.
006我们要做很多有趣的事情。
So today's lecture today's lecture is a light lecture,
所以今天的演讲今天的演讲是一个简短的演讲
I would even call it a recreational mathematics
我什至称它为休闲数学
lecture.
演讲。
And so, thanks for coming.
因此，感谢您的光临。
I'll make it worth your while, all right?
我值得您花时间，好吗？
So we're going to talk about irrationals.
因此，我们将讨论非理性。
The motivation behind this is really that every
背后的动机实际上是每个人
once in awhile we are going to have a situation where
偶尔我们会有一种情况
we want to compute with numbers that are much longer than 64
我们要使用远大于64的数字进行计算
bits, which is really the word length in standard computer
位，实际上是标准计算机中的字长
these days.
这些日子。
It used to be 8 bits back in the day.
过去是8位。
For most of my adult life it was 32 bits.
在我成年的大部分时间里，它都是32位。
And recently Intel and AMD have gone to 64-bit processors.
最近，英特尔和AMD已采用64位处理器。
But 64 bits ain't near enough if you
但是，如果您有64位，那还不够
want to do what's called high precision computation, you want
想做所谓的高精度计算，
to find precisely the weight of a neutrino,
精确地找到中微子的重量
if you're a physicist, for example.
例如，如果您是物理学家。
And that, you're talking about literally a hundred
那就是您所说的一百
decimal digits, which is obviously
十进制数字，这显然是
much more than 64 bits.
远远超过64位。
And that's just one example.
那只是一个例子。
So what happens if you want to compute the square root of 2
那么如果要计算2的平方根会发生什么
to a million digits, or pi to 10 million digits?
到一百万个数字，或pi到一千万个数字？
How do you do that on a computer?
您如何在计算机上执行此操作？
So that's what we're going to do for this module, which
这就是我们要为该模块做的
is a short module on numerics.
是数字的简短模块。
We'll have a lecture today and another one on Tuesday
我们今天要上课，星期二再上课
telling you about techniques that use, among other things,
告诉您有关使用的技术，
Newton's method to compute irrational numbers, as one
牛顿计算无理数的方法
example, to arbitrary precision And for your problem set
例如，以任意精度并针对您的问题集
you are you going to look at different application that
你要去看看不同的应用程序
corresponds to encryption, RSA encryption,
对应于加密，RSA加密，
where you have to work with primes.
您必须使用素数的地方。
These are now integers, but you work with primes
现在这些是整数，但是您可以使用质数
that are thousands of bits long, so again,
几千位长，所以再次
much more than 64 bits.
远远超过64位。
And so you have to think about how you're
因此，您必须考虑自己的状况
going to multiply numbers that are thousands of bits
将要乘以数千位的数字
long, how you're going to divide numbers that are thousands
长，如何划分成千上万的数字
of bits long, and that's really the purpose of this module.
的长度，这才是本模块的目的。
So let's start off by talking about irrationals.
因此，让我们从谈论非理性开始。
And Pythagoras, whom I'm sure you've all heard of
还有毕达哥拉斯，我相信你们都听说过
is credited with the discovery that a square's diagonal
被认为是正方形的对角线
and its side are incommensurable.
它的一面无与伦比。
So you can't really express the ratio as a rational number,
因此，您无法真正将比率表示为有理数，
as a ratio of integers.
作为整数的比率。
Now it turns out that the Babylonians and the Indians
现在事实证明，巴比伦人和印第安人
knew this way before Pythagoras, but he
在毕达哥拉斯之前就知道这种方式，但是他
gets credit for the Pythagoras theorem.
获得毕达哥拉斯定理的功劳。
And there's also a Greek philosopher,
还有一位希腊哲学家，
in fact, maybe he was first a philosopher and then
实际上，也许他首先是哲学家，然后
a mathematician, and he the espoused a philosophy
数学家，他拥护一种哲学
that, I guess, is called Pythagorean mysticism, that
我猜这就是毕达哥拉斯的神秘主义，
said that all is number, so the world is about numbers.
说一切都是数字，所以世界就是数字。
And he worshipped numbers, his followers worshipped numbers.
他崇拜数字，他的追随者也崇拜数字。
And the problem here was that he didn't really
这里的问题是他并没有真正
like the square root of 2 because he couldn't express it
像2的平方根一样，因为他无法表达
as a number, of what he thought of as a number, which was 1, 2,
他认为数字是1、2
3, et cetera, integers, whole numbers.
3，等等，整数，整数。
So he called this ratio speechless,
所以他说这个比例无语，
something that he really couldn't explain.
他真的无法解释的事情。
And irrationals were actually considered a threat
非理性的人实际上被认为是威胁
to the mystics because they couldn't really
神秘主义者，因为他们不能真正
explain what square root of 2 was.
解释2的平方根是多少。
They'd try and measure it, and they would come up
他们会尝试进行测量，然后他们会提出
with the right answer because the next time around it
正确的答案，因为下次
would be a little bit different If they did things
如果他们做事会有些不同
a little more precisely, or not so precisely.
稍微精确一点，或者不那么精确。
And it bothered them no end.
这无休止地困扰着他们。
And so they tried to find patterns in irrationals
所以他们试图找到非理性的模式
because they considered them a threat.
因为他们认为它们是威胁。
And they obviously didn't find patterns,
而且他们显然没有找到模式，
but imagine if we could actually find patterns.
但是想象一下我们是否真的可以找到模式。
I mean, that would be a really big deal,
我的意思是，那将是非常重要的，
it would be better than p equals np, if you know what I mean.
如果您知道我的意思，那将比p等于np好。
If you don't it doesn't matter.
如果不这样做，没关系。
So that's another of motivation for high precision arithmetic.
因此，这是高精度算术的另一动力。
Let's try and find patterns in irrationals
让我们尝试找到非理性的模式
if you go to millions and trillions of digits,
如果您达到数百万亿万位数，
maybe it's just a matter of time before we discover that there's
也许只是时间问题，我们才发现
no such thing as irrational numbers.
没有非理性数字之类的东西。
Who knows?
谁知道？
So let's do that for the rest of this lecture.
因此，在本讲座的其余部分中，请继续进行操作。
Let's try and figure out how we're
让我们尝试弄清楚我们如何
going to compute irrational numbers, or things
要计算无理数或事物
like square root of 2, to arbitrary precision.
像2的平方根一样，达到任意精度。
So we can go play around, and we'll give you some code,
这样我们就可以玩了，我们会给您一些代码，
and you can play with it.
你可以玩
So if you look at square root of 2--
因此，如果您查看2--的平方根
I'll just put this up here-- so it's 1.414,
我将其放在此处-就是1.414，
you probably all know that.
你们可能都知道。
Then it's 213,562,373,095,048 et cetera.
然后是213,562,373,095,048等。
I mean, I don't see a pattern there.
我的意思是，我在那里看不到任何模式。
I see a zero, a couple of zeroes here.
我在这里看到一个零，几个零。
It's hard to imagine-- you'd probably
很难想象-您可能会
want to think of a computer program that generates
想想一个生成的计算机程序
square root of 2, and then maybe a different computer
2的平方根，然后可能是另一台计算机
program that's looking for patterns.
寻找模式的程序。
So let's not worry about the square root of 2.
因此，不必担心2的平方根。
I want to digress a little bit.
我想讲一点点。
I did say this was a bit of a recreational mathematics
我确实说过这是一种娱乐数学
lecture.
演讲。
And let's talk about something completely different,
让我们谈谈完全不同的东西，
which are Catalan numbers.
这是加泰罗尼亚语数字。
So these are really my favorite numbers in the world.
因此，这些确实是我在世界上最喜欢的数字。
And people like primes, some people like irrationals,
人们喜欢素数，有些人喜欢非理性，
I like Catalan numbers.
我喜欢加泰罗尼亚语数字。
Catalan numbers are-- they show up all over the place.
加泰罗尼亚语的数字遍布整个地方。
How many of you know what Catalan numbers are?
你们当中有多少人知道加泰罗尼亚语数字是什么？
Oh good.
很好
Excellent.
优秀的。
So Catalan numbers have a recursive definition.
因此，加泰罗尼亚语数字具有递归定义。
You can think of them as representing the cardinality
您可以认为它们代表基数
of the set p of balanced parentheses strings.
平衡括号串的集合p的值。
And we're going to recursively define
我们将递归定义
these strings as follows.
这些字符串如下。
We're going to have lambda belonging
我们将拥有lambda
to p where lambda is the empty string.
到p，其中lambda是空字符串。
And that's rule one.
那是规则之一。
Rule two is if alpha and beta belong
规则二是alpha和beta是否属于
to p then I'm going to put a paren, open paren, alpha,
p然后我要放一个括号，打开括号，alpha，
close paren, and then beta.
关闭paren，然后是beta。
And that belongs to p.
那属于p。
So you iteratively or recursively apply this rule
因此，您可以迭代或递归地应用此规则
over and over, and you start getting
一遍又一遍，你开始
strings that are balanced.
平衡的弦。
So this is balanced.
因此，这是平衡的。
Now that's not balanced, this is not
现在不平衡，这不是
balanced, and so on and so forth.
平衡等等。
Obviously things get more complicated
显然事情变得更加复杂
in terms of the parentheses if when you have more brackets
用括号括起来，如果有更多括号
or parentheses.
或括号。
And so, the nice thing about this definition
因此，关于此定义的好处
is that you can get every non-empty balanced paren
就是你可以得到所有非空的平衡货币
string, via rule two, from a unique alpha, beta pair.
通过规则二从唯一的alpha，beta对中输入字符串。
So as an example, suppose you want
例如，假设您要
to generate the string that looks like this--
生成看起来像这样的字符串-
So that's a little more complicated than the strings
所以这比字符串要复杂一些
that we have looked at so far-- then you
到目前为止我们已经看过了-那么您
obtain that by having alpha be this simple string.
通过使alpha为该简单字符串来获得该值。
And then you put the brackets around that, and then
然后将括号放在该位置，然后
your beta corresponds to this.
您的Beta与此对应。
So now alpha and beta were previously generated,
所以现在已经生成了alpha和beta，
so if you applied rule two to the empty string,
因此，如果您将规则2应用于空字符串，
with alpha being the empty string
其中alpha是空字符串
and beta being the empty string, then you get this thing here.
和beta是空字符串，那么您在这里得到了这个东西。
And obviously you could get beta by setting
显然，您可以通过设置
alpha to be the empty string and beta to be this string that you
alpha为空字符串，beta为该字符串
just generated, and so on and so forth.
刚刚生成的，依此类推。
So you just keep going and the strings get longer and longer.
因此，只要继续前进，弦线就会越来越长。
The cardinality of the set gets bigger and bigger.
集合的基数越来越大。
And those of the Catalan numbers.
还有那些加泰罗尼亚语的数字。
OK
好
And so, this is a non-trivial question,
因此，这是一个不平凡的问题，
which is I'd like to enumerate the Catalan numbers,
我想列举加泰罗尼亚语的数字，
and compute, and get an analytical form
并计算，并获得分析表格
for the cardinality of the set.
集合的基数。
And that's really what the Catalan number is.
这就是加泰罗尼亚语的数字。
It's a cardinality of the set.
这是集合的基数。
And so cn is the number of balanced parentheses strings
所以cn是平衡括号字符串的数量
with exactly n pairs of parentheses.
正好有n对括号。
And I have c0 equals 1, which is my base case.
我的c0等于1，这是我的基本情况。
And that's just setting-- it's an empty string.
这只是设置-这是一个空字符串。
I'm going to say that empty string is a string,
我要说的是空字符串是一个字符串，
and that's just setting up the base case.
这只是设置基本情况。
And now I want an equation for cn plus 1.
现在我想要一个cn加1的方程。
And I need to use the fact that I
我需要利用我
can get cn plus 1, a particular strain that belongs
可以得到cn加1，属于
to this set, where I have n plus 1 parenthesis in a unique way
在这个集合中，我以独特的方式有n加1个括号
from a string I've previously generated that was part
从我之前生成的字符串中
of either the set that had n parentheses--
有n个括号的集合中的一个-
or it was combined using strings, where alpha was
或使用字符串组合，其中alpha为
in some set that was maybe generated awhile
在某些情况下可能会产生一段时间
back with a small n, or something
返回一个小n或其他东西
significantly smaller than n, and another thing that
明显小于n，另一件事是
was generated, beta, that was generated later,
生成了Beta，后来又生成了
or maybe at the same time, et cetera.
或同时，等等。
So can someone tell me what an equation would be for cn plus 1
有人可以告诉我cn加1的方程是什么
based on the cis that are less than n?
基于小于n的顺式？
So what about c1?
那么c1呢？
Maybe I'll ask-- what about c1?
也许我会问-关于c1呢？
What's c1?
什么是c1？
1.
1。
c1 is 1 because all I have is this string, that's
c1是1，因为我只有这个字符串，那是
the only balanced string.
唯一的平衡弦。
Now I have c0 and c1.
现在我有c0和c1。
What's an equation for c2 in terms of numbers.
关于c2的数字方程式。
I want a number for c2 based on c0 and c1.
我想要一个基于c0和c1的c2的数字。
Someone?
有人吗
Yeah.
是的
AUDIENCE: C0 plus c1.
听众：C0加c1。
PROFESSOR: c0 plus c1?
教授：c0加c1？
No, not quite right.
不，不太正确。
How many strings do I have?
我有几根琴弦？
c0 plus c1.
c0加c1。
Yeah, actually you're right.
是的，实际上您是对的。
Well, the number is right but the equation is wrong.
好吧，这个数字是正确的，但是方程式是错误的。
It's not quite that.
不是那样的
You get a-- Yup.
你得到-是的。
AUDIENCE: So when something like c-- c1 times c1 plus c1.
听众：所以当c– c1乘以c1加c1时。
PROFESSOR: c1 times c1 plus c1?
教授：c1乘以c1加c1？
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
听众：是的。
PROFESSOR: I think you want to use a c0.
教授：我认为您想使用c0。
AUDIENCE: OK. c0.
听众：好的。 c0。
PROFESSOR: c0 Well, that's not quite right either.
教授：c0嗯，那也不完全正确。
Someone else.
其他人。
Yeah.
是的
OK.
好。
You.
您。
AUDIENCE: c0 times c1 plus c1 [INAUDIBLE].
听众：c0乘以c1加c1 [听不清]。
PROFESSOR: c0 times c1-- c2 would
教授：c0乘以c1-- c2
be c0 times c1 plus c1 times c0.
是c0乘以c1乘以c1乘以c0。
OK.
好。
And if you're setting the alpha-- So here's the thing,
如果您要设置Alpha，那么事情就在这里，
you set the alpha, and you choose the alpha,
您设置Alpha，然后选择Alpha，
and then you choose the beta.
然后选择Beta。
And there's a couple of different ways
有两种不同的方式
that you could choose the alpha.
您可以选择Alpha。
You could choose the alpha from-- you
您可以选择-
could make it a string that's empty,
可以将其设置为空字符串，
or you could make it the one string
或者你可以把它变成一个字符串
that you've generated so far, which
到目前为止，您已经生成了
is the standard simple string, the non-empty,
是标准的简单字符串，非空，
the non-trivial balanced string.
非平凡的平衡弦。
And you could do that in a couple different ways
您可以通过几种不同的方式
with alpha.
与阿尔法。
And that's why you have two terms over there.
这就是为什么在那边有两个条件的原因。
So the number, in terms of all of the equations I got,
因此，就我得到的所有方程式而言，
they all came out to be the same.
他们都出来都是一样的。
It's 2, and that's correct.
是2，是正确的。
But this is the equation for it.
但这就是方程式。
And so now, tell me what a general equation
所以现在，告诉我什么是一般方程
is for cn plus 1 based on what we've
是基于我们的cn加1
learned so far for the c2 equation?
到目前为止，对于c2方程了解到了什么？
Yeah, back to you.
是的，回到你身边。
AUDIENCE: So c0 times cn plus c1 times cn
观众：所以c0乘以cn加c1乘以cn
minus 1 all the way to cn times [INAUDIBLE].
一直减负1直到cn次[音频不清晰]。
PROFESSOR: Perfect.
教授：完美。
Good.
好。
That deserves a cushion.
那值得缓冲。
That wasn't me, it was you.
那不是我，是你。
And put it right there, breadbasket.
然后放到那里，粮仓。
So cn plus 1 equals sigma, so you give me a summation,
所以cn加1等于sigma，所以您求和
k equals 0 through n, ck, cn minus k where
k等于0到n，ck，cn减去k，其中
n is greater than or equal to 0.
n大于或等于0。
And you can figure this out, it's not particularly important
您可以弄清楚，这并不是特别重要
as to exactly why this is true.
到底为什么这是真的。
You can think about it offline.
您可以离线考虑。
But the interesting thing is that this is a generator of,
有趣的是，这是
obviously, and it's going to give you
显然，它将给你
a nice looking set of numbers.
一组漂亮的数字。
And I came in early and wrote that the Catalan in numbers
我很早就来写了加泰罗尼亚语
up on the board going from c0, c1, c2, et cetera, just
从c0，c1，c2等开始，
in case-- just in case you ever see these numbers in real life,
以防万一，以防万一您在现实生活中看到这些数字，
or when you're writing computer programs.
或在编写计算机程序时。
Or you're driving on the road, the next time you see a license
或者您下次在道路上开车时，您会看到驾照
plate 4862, turn around and tell your mom or dad, hey,
盘4862，转身告诉你的妈妈或爸爸，嘿，
that's the Catalan number.
那是加泰罗尼亚语的数字。
And maybe she'll be impressed.
也许她会留下深刻的印象。
This, of course, you're not going
当然，你不会
to see on a license plate, but you can always
可以在车牌上看到，但您始终可以
make up a bumper sticker or something,
补上保险杠之类的东西，
and you can have the c17 as being
您可以将c17作为
a bumper sticker on your car.
汽车上的保险杠贴纸。
I mean, that's the kind of thing that I'd do.
我的意思是，这就是我要做的事情。
Anyway, so it's just in case you see these numbers--
无论如何，以防万一您看到这些数字-
we might come back to this a little bit later in the class,
我们可能会在课堂上稍后再讲到这一点，
but--
但 -
AUDIENCE: 42 is on that list.
听众：42在那个名单上。
PROFESSOR: 42 is on that list.
教授：这个清单上有42个。
Yeah, it has to be.
是的，一定是。
42 is on every list.
每个列表中有42个。
42 is the answer to every question.
42是每个问题的答案。
I am glad you guys didn't put 42 down in the answer
我很高兴你们没有在答案中写下42
to every quiz question.
每个测验问题。
It doesn't quite work all the time, all right,
它不是一直都在工作，好吧，
but most of the time 42 is a good answer.
但是大多数时候42是一个很好的答案。
Most of the time.
大多数时候。
OK good.
好的
So let's get down to business.
因此，让我们开始做生意。
So we talked about Catalan numbers as a digression.
因此，我们谈到加泰罗尼亚语数字是题外话。
If you see them you'll recognize them, I think.
我想，如果看到它们，您就会认出它们。
Let's talk about how we could compute.
让我们谈谈如何计算。
Let's go back to irrationals and talk
让我们回到非理性的话题
about how we could compute square root of 2
关于如何计算2的平方根
and other things to arbitrary precision.
和其他东西达到任意精度。
So what I want to do is to talk about Newton's method.
所以我想谈的是牛顿法。
And Newton's method is something you probably
牛顿的方法可能就是你
learned about in middle school, high school.
在中学，高中就知道了。
And let's say you have a function
假设您有一个功能
y equals f of x where this is x and that's
y等于x的f，其中x是
y, the coordinate axes.
y，坐标轴。
And we want to try and find the root of fx equals 0
我们想尝试找出fx的根等于0
through successive approximation.
通过逐次逼近
For example, we might have f of x equals x squared minus a.
例如，我们的x的f等于x平方减去a。
And if a is 2 then you're trying to use Newton's method
如果a为2，则您正在尝试使用牛顿方法
to find the root, and you're going
找到根，你要去
to end up trying to compute square root of 2 or plus
最终试图计算2或加的平方根
minus square root of 2, in this case.
在这种情况下，减去2的平方根。
But you can go for a particular root,
但是您可以选择特定的根源，
and you're try and converge to that.
而您正在努力收敛。
So the way Newton's method works is it tries, geometrically
因此，牛顿方法的工作方式是尝试几何
speaking, it tries to find tangents--
讲，它试图找到切线
and a different color chalk would be useful here
在这里用不同颜色的粉笔会很有用
but I don't seem to see one-- So what would happen
但我似乎没有看到-那么会发生什么
is, let's say you are sitting out here,
是，假设您坐在这里，
and it's successive approximation method,
它是逐次逼近法
so this would give you x of i.
因此，这将给您x i。
And now you want to compute x of i plus 1.
现在您要计算x的i加1。
And what you're going to do is draw a tangent,
然后您要做的就是画一条切线，
like so, and find the intercept onto the x-axis,
像这样，找到在x轴上的截距，
the x-intercept.
X截距。
And that is going to be your xi plus 1.
那将是您的xi加1。
And you have to write an equation for that tangent.
而且您必须为该切线编写一个方程式。
And this is, I guess, trying to figure
我想这就是尝试
out how much of middle school math or high school math
找出多少中学数学或高中数学
that you remember.
你记得。
What is the equation for that tangent?
该切线的方程是什么？
Anybody?
有人吗
The equation for that tangent?
该切线的方程式？
What do you do in order to compute that tangent?
您要做什么才能计算该切线？
Give me a name.
给我一个名字。
AUDIENCE: Derivative?
听众：衍生品？
PROFESSOR: Derivative.
教授：导数。
Thank you.
谢谢。
So what's the equation for that tangent?
那么该切线的方程是什么？
y equals-- Someone?
y等于-有人吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
PROFESSOR: It's a good think your middle school,
教授：很高兴您的中学，
high school teachers aren't here.
高中老师不在。
Not you.
不是你。
You already got a cushion.
你已经坐垫了。
Someone else.
其他人。
All right.
好吧。
I'll start giving you some hints here.
我将在这里开始给您一些提示。
f of xi plus-- plus--
xi的f加-加-
ALL: f prime.
全部：f素数。
PROFESSOR: f prime xi.
教授：f prime xi。
Thank you.
谢谢。
All right.
好吧。
You get a cushion.
你会得到缓冲。
I'm getting them.
我要他们。
Whatever it takes.
不惜一切代价。
Here you go.
干得好。
Yeah.
是的
That was left-handed, by the way.
顺便说一句，那是左撇子。
I'm actually right-handed, as you know.
如您所知，我实际上是右撇子。
So what do we have here?
那我们这里有什么？
So we have f prime xi.
因此，我们有素数xi。
Now come on, let's finish it, finish it.
现在来，让我们完成它，完成它。
AUDIENCE: Times i minus xi.
听众：我减去xi的次数。
PROFESSOR: Times xi is xi.
教授：时代xi是xi。
Thank you.
谢谢。
OK.
好。
So now I get it.
所以现在我明白了。
You thought this was too simple a question.
您认为这是一个太简单的问题。
You guys were insulted by the question.
你们被这个问题侮辱了。
So that's why you didn't tell me what it was At least, that's
所以这就是为什么你没有告诉我那是什么原因至少，那是
what I'm going to pretend to make myself feel better.
我要假装使自己感觉好些。
So y equals f of xi plus f prime xi,
因此y等于xi的f加上f素数xi，
which is the derivative of f evaluated at xi times
这是在xi次评估的f的导数
x minus xi, that's the equation for the line.
x减去xi，即直线的方程式。
And that's essentially what we have
这基本上就是我们所拥有的
to do to compute things like square root of 2, which
进行计算，例如2的平方根
is iteratively applied Newton's method.
反复应用牛顿法。
The only problem is this is all good in theory
唯一的问题是，从理论上讲，这一切都很好
that we can do-- take that equation turn it into xi
我们可以做的-将该等式变成xi
plus 1 equals xi minus f of xi divided by f prime of xi.
加1等于xi减去xi的f除以xi的f素数。
And if you end up doing f of x equals x squared minus a, then
并且如果最后做x的f等于x平方减去a，则
you have xi plus 1 equals xi minus xi
您有xi加1等于xi减去xi
squared minus a divided by 2xi, which is the derivative of x
减去a的平方除以2xi，即x的导数
squared minus a evaluated at xi.
在xi处减去的平方减去a。
And finally you get this equation, xi
最后得到这个方程，xi
plus a divided by xi divided by 2.
加除以xi除以2。
So it's fairly straightforward.
因此，这非常简单。
xi plus 1 equals xi plus a divided by xi divided by 2.
xi加1等于xi加除以xi除以2。
And if you look at this, remember
如果你看这个，记住
that a is typically a small number.
通常是一个很小的数字。
I mean, it's two, in this case, if you're
我的意思是，如果您是
computing square root of 2.
计算2的平方根。
it may even be an integer, maybe a fraction.
它甚至可以是整数，也可以是分数。
But you have to do a division here.
但是您必须在这里进行划分。
And remember that since we want to compute things
记住，因为我们要计算事物
to millions of digits, potentially, these numbers,
数以百万计的数字，可能是这些数字，
the xi numbers, are going to have millions of digits.
xi数将具有数百万个数字。
And so if you end up running this Newton method
因此，如果最终运行此牛顿方法
on a equals 2, then if I simulate what
等于2，那么如果我模拟
happens without worrying about the implementation,
无需担心实施，
and this is what you'll get.
这就是你所得到的。
You have x0-- you start with x0 equals 1 with a bunch of zeros.
您有x0-您以x0开头等于一串零。
xi equals 1.5 with a bunch of zeros, et cetera.
xi等于1.5，带有一串零，等等。
And then, x2 equals 1.41666 et cetera.
然后，x2等于1.41666等。
That goes on.
那继续。
And we're not talking about fractions here,
而且我们这里不是在谈论分数
we're talking about floating point numbers that
我们谈论的是浮点数
are integers with a certain amount of precision.
是具有一定精度的整数。
So you've decided that you want to compute this
所以您已经决定要计算
to d digits of precision where d may be a million.
到d位精度，其中d可能是一百万。
And so, really, here you would have a representation that's
所以，真的，在这里您将得到一个表示
a million digits long that where,
一百万位数长，
basically, everything is zero, and here everything but one
基本上，一切都是零，这里除了一个
is 0, or maybe a couple if you count the 1 here.
是0，如果在这里算1，可能是一对。
And here you have all these sixes here,
在这里，您拥有所有这些六分力，
and so on and so forth.
等等等等。
And you keep going, and you get x2 equals 1.414215686.
然后继续前进，得到的x2等于1.414215686。
And I want to write one more because I
我想再写一封，因为我
want to point out something that's important.
想指出重要的事情。
1.414213562.
1.414213562。
And what's nice about this, if you go compare it
如果这样做比较有什么好处
with what you have up there, is that you
你在那里所拥有的是你
have quadratic convergence using the Newton's method.
使用牛顿法进行二次收敛。
And what do I mean by that?
我的意思是什么？
Well, quadratic convergence is a nice property.
二次收敛是一个很好的特性。
It's much better than linear convergence.
它比线性收敛好得多。
Linear convergence would mean that you
线性收敛将意味着您
get an extra digit of precision for every iteration.
每次迭代都获得额外的精度。
So in this case, actually, a quadratic is better.
因此，在这种情况下，实际上，二次方更好。
Usually we think of quadratic algorithms,
通常我们会想到二次算法
and we are going to throw up.
而且我们要吐了。
But linear algorithms is what we like.
但是我们喜欢线性算法。
But in this case it's actually a good thing.
但是在这种情况下，这实际上是一件好事。
You have this extended this quadratic rate of convergence
您已经扩展了这种二次收敛速度
where the number of digits that are correct
正确的位数
doubles with every iteration, as you can see.
如您所见，每次迭代都会加倍。
So here you have-- you start with, roughly,
因此，在这里-您大致从
if you rounded this up you would get 5.
如果将其四舍五入，将得到5。
So you're saying that that's one digit of precision
所以你说的是精度的一位数
in terms of the decimal.
以小数表示。
And then, now you're talking about 41421356,
然后，您现在谈论的是41421356，
so that's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8,
所以是1、2、3、4、5、6、7、8
so that's eight digits of precision here, four here,
所以这里的精度是八位数，这里的是四位数，
and so on and so forth.
等等等等。
So that's nice.
很好。
That's why the Newton's method is actually
这就是为什么牛顿法实际上是
used in practice because the number of digits doubles.
在实践中使用，因为位数翻倍。
This is a precision.
这是一个精度。
So now you don't get too scared about calculating things
所以现在您不必太担心计算
that are a million because you kind of go and say, whoa,
那是一百万，因为你会说，哇，
I mean, that's not so bad, that's only
我的意思是，还不错，只是
a logarithmic number of integrations.
对数的积分。
And it's not like you have to run for a million iterations.
而且，您不必运行一百万次迭代。
You go 2, 4, 8, 16, and now that exponential helps you,
您进行了2、4、8、16运算，现在，指数可以帮助您，
the geometric series helps you.
几何系列可以为您提供帮助。
So that's the nice thing about the Newton's method.
这就是牛顿法的优点。
Haven't quite told you how we are
还没完全告诉你我们怎么样
going to compute the most important thing here
在这里计算最重要的事情
with respect to a divided by xi.
关于除以xi。
So this is just additions.
所以这只是补充。
You can imagine that if you have long numbers
你可以想像，如果你有很多数字
you'd end up doing addition fairly straightforwardly
你最终会很直接地做加法
because you only have to worry about one carry,
因为您只需要担心一个进位，
and so you go off.
所以你走了。
And I'm sure you've added up numbers
我确定你已经加了数字
that are in tens, if not hundreds, of digits long
数位（如果不是几百个）长
but I'm guessing you haven't manually
但我猜你不是手动
multiplied numbers that are hundreds of digits long.
乘以数百位数的数字。
And if you have I'd be impressed,
如果有的话，我会印象深刻，
though I won't believe your result.
尽管我不会相信你的结果。
But that's something that is kind of a painful thing to do.
但这是一件痛苦的事情。
And so that's why we need computers.
这就是为什么我们需要计算机。
And that's multiplication and-- has anybody
那就是乘法，并且-有任何人
divided a hundred-digit number by another 50-digit number?
用一个100位数字除以另一个50位数字？
No.
没有。
So you need computers.
因此，您需要计算机。
So we've got to be able to do that division there,
所以我们必须能够在那里进行分区，
a divided by xi, using computers.
用计算机除以xi。
And so that's really the purpose of this and the next lecture
因此，这正是本课以及下一讲的目的
If you're only going to do a high precision
如果您只想做高精度
multiplication here.
这里乘法。
And try see what an algorithm would be for high precision
并尝试了解高精度算法
multiplication because what we're going to do
乘法，因为我们要做的是
is, essentially, take the reciprocal of one over xi
从本质上讲，是xi的倒数
and then multiply that by a.
然后将其乘以a。
And we need-- division is going to require multiplication.
我们需要-除法将需要乘法。
You don't really see a multiplication
你真的看不到乘法
there other than a times 1 over xi.
除xi的1倍以外。
And you can say, well, do we really need multiplication?
你可以说，嗯，我们真的需要乘法吗？
Well, the answer is the division algorithm
好吧，答案是除法算法
that is used in practice in most division algorithms have
在大多数除法算法中实际使用的
multiplication as a subroutine.
乘法作为子例程。
So we're going to have to figure out high precision
所以我们必须找出高精度
multiplication first-- It's a little bit easier
首先进行乘法-稍微容易一点
than division-- and use it as a subroutine for high precision
比除法-并将其用作高精度子程序
division, which we'll do next time.
部门，我们下次再做。
So now we're sort of back in 006 land, if you will.
所以现在，如果您愿意，我们有点回到006土地。
We have a problem that is high precision multiplication,
我们有一个问题，就是高精度乘法
and we want to find an algorithm for it.
我们想找到一种算法。
And there's the vanilla algorithm
还有香草算法
that is going to take certain amounts of time,
这将花费一定的时间，
asymptotically speaking, and then there
渐近地讲，然后在那里
is better and better algorithms.
是越来越好的算法。
As you can imagine, multiplication
可以想象，乘法
is just such a fundamental operation
就是这么基本的操作
that people have looked at trying
人们已经看过尝试
to reduce the complexity of high precision multiplication.
降低高精度乘法的复杂度。
So if you have n bits-- So what is the standard algorithm
所以如果你有n位-那么标准算法是什么
for multiplication take if you have n bits of precision?
如果您有n位精度，则需要乘法吗？
AUDIENCE: N squared.
听众：N平方。
PROFESSOR: n squared.
教授：n平方。
But you can do better.
但是你可以做得更好。
And the people are work on it.
人们正在为此努力。
You can do fast Fourier transforms.
您可以进行快速傅立叶变换。
We won't quite do that here.
我们不会在这里做到这一点。
If you take 6.046 you'll probably learn about that.
如果您采用6.046，您可能会学到更多。
But we'll do a couple of algorithms
但是我们将做一些算法
that are better than the order n squared method,
比阶数n平方的方法更好，
and we'll do one of those today.
我们今天将做其中之一。
So the way they're going to work with integers--
因此，他们使用整数的方式-
one little point that I need to make before we move ahead here
在我们继续前进之前，我需要提出一点
is, generally, we going to say, for the purposes of 006,
一般来说，就006而言，
that we know the digits of precision up front because we
我们知道预先的精度数字，因为我们
want d digits of precision, maybe it's 42, maybe it's 125.
想要d位精度，也许是42，也许是125。
In the case of our problem set in RSA we going to have it
对于我们在RSA中设置的问题，我们将拥有它
1,024-bit numbers, maybe 2,048.
1,024位数字，也许是2,048。
So we know d beforehand.
所以我们事先知道d。
And so what we want is an integer, which
所以我们想要的是一个整数
is 10 raised to d times the square root of 2, a floor,
是10上升到d乘以2的平方根，即地板，
and which is essentially the same as that, 2 times 10 raised
基本上是一样的，加注2乘10
to 2 d.
至2 d。
So we're going to treat these as integers,
因此，我们将这些视为整数，
so we don't want to worry about decimal points
所以我们不想担心小数点
and things like that.
之类的。
All of these things are going to be integers.
所有这些都将是整数。
And there's no problem here.
而且这里没有问题。
We can still use Newton's method.
我们仍然可以使用牛顿法。
It just works on integers.
它仅适用于整数。
And let's take a look at how we would
让我们来看看我们将如何
apply Newton's method in standard form.
以标准形式应用牛顿法。
And we won't to really get to the part
而且我们不会真正地参与其中
where we're going to go from division to multiplication
我们要从除法到乘法的地方
today, as I said, we're just going
今天，正如我说的，我们要去
to look at how you can multiply two numbers.
看看如何将两个数字相乘。
So I didn't mean to say that we're
所以我不是故意要说我们
going to look at Newton's method.
来看看牛顿的方法。
We're going to look at high precision multiplication,
我们将研究高精度乘法，
and then, eventually, we're going
然后，最终，我们要
to use that to build Newton's method
用它来建立牛顿法
which requires the division.
这需要分裂。
So I have two n-digit numbers, and the radix
所以我有两个n位数字和基数
could be-- the base could be 2, 10.
可能是-底数可以是2、10
Normally, it doesn't really matter.
通常，这并不重要。
0 less than x, less than y, strictly less than r
0小于x，小于y，严格小于r
raised to n.
升到n
That's standard for the ranges.
这是范围的标准。
And what I have here is-- the way
我在这里的是-方式
I'm going to do this is use our favorite strategy, which
我要做的就是使用我们最喜欢的策略
is divide and conquer, because I have n, which is large,
是分而治之，因为我有n，它很大，
need to break things down, break it into n
需要分解，分解成n
by two-digit multiplications.
两位数相乘。
And when, finally, I break things down,
最后，当我分解事情时，
I get down to 64 bits, I just run one instruction
我下降到64位，我只运行一条指令
on my computer to multiply the 64-bit numbers.
在我的计算机上将64位数字相乘。
And the standard machines, you would get 128 bits of result
在标准机器上，您将获得128位结果
back when you multiply 64-bit numbers.
当您乘以64位数字时返回。
So in some sense you only go down--
所以从某种意义上说，你只会下去-
you don't go down to 1 bit, you go down to 64
您不会下降到1位，而是下降到64位
and your machine does the rest.
剩下的事由您的机器完成。
So what we have here is you set x to be x1
所以我们这里是将x设置为x1
where x1 is the high half, r raised to n over 2 plus x0.
其中x1是上半部分，r在2加x0的基础上提高到n。
So x1 is the more significant half and x0 is the low half.
因此，x1是较高的一半，x0是较低的一半。
And the same thing for y.
和y同样。
y1, whoops, r raised to n over 2 plus y0.
y1，哎呀，r在2加y0的基础上提高到n。
Now the ranges change.
现在范围改变了。
x0 and x1 are smaller, so that's what you have for x0 and x1.
x0和x1较小，所以这就是x0和x1的大小。
Same thing for y0 and y1.
y0和y1同样。
So that's a fairly straightforward decomposition
这是一个相当简单的分解
of this multiplication operation.
这个乘法运算。
And again, if you do things in a straightforward way
再说一次，如果您以直截了当的方式做事
you will create a recursive multiply, as I'll write here.
您将创建一个递归乘法，就像我在这里写的那样。
And what you do is you say let z0 equal x0 times y0,
而你要做的就是说让z0等于x0乘以y0，
z two equals x2 times y2, and-- I missed z1,
z等于x2乘以y2，并且-我错过了z1，
but z1 equals x0, y1 plus x1 y0.
但是z1等于x0，y1加上x1 y0。
And I have, overall, z equals y equals
总的来说，我等于z等于y等于
x1 y1 times r raised to n plus x0 y1 plus x1 y0 times
x1 y1倍r升至n加x0 y1加x1 y0倍
r raised to n over 2 plus x0 y0 zero.
r在2加上x0 y0零时升至n。
And this part here was z0, this part here was z1,
这部分是z0，这部分是z1，
and this part here was z2.
这部分是z2
And if you look at, it you need four multiplies, 1, 2, 3, 4.
如果您看一下，它需要四个乘法，即1、2、3、4。
And you need four multiplies of n
你需要n的四个乘积
by two-- n by two-digit numbers.
用两位数-n用两位数表示。
And by now, after you have prepared for quiz two,
到现在为止，在您准备了第二场测验之后，
I will just say that it would take theta n square time
我只想说这将花费平方时间
because you're recursive equation
因为你是递归方程
is tn equals 4t of n over 2 plus the linear time that you take
tn等于2上n的4t加上您花费的线性时间
for addition.
用于添加。
So this is tn equals 4t of n over 2 plus theta n.
因此，tn等于2上的n的4t加theta n。
And you're assuming that the additions here
而且您假设这里的添加项
take linear time.
花费线性时间。
So that's how you get your theta n square algorithm.
这样便可以得到theta n square算法。
And we're not happy with that.
我们对此不满意。
We'd like to do better.
我们想做得更好。
And so how do you do better?
那么您如何做得更好？
Well, there's many ways of doing better.
好吧，有很多方法可以做得更好。
The simplest way off fairly, substantially lowering
最简单的方法是公平，大幅降低
the complexity is due to a gentleman
复杂性是由于一位绅士
by the name of Karatsuba.
用唐津巴的名字
This is one of those things where
这是其中的一件事
if you were born early enough you
如果你出生得早
get your name on an algorithm.
通过算法获得您的名字。
And what happens here is, using the z's that I have out there,
然后发生的是，使用我在那里的z
you essentially say, look, I know z0 equals x0 and y0,
您基本上是说，看，我知道z0等于x0和y0，
I'm going to go ahead and multiply.
我要继续繁殖。
z2 equals x2 and y2, go ahead and do that.
z2等于x2和y2，继续做。
And now I'm going to write z1 as x0 plus x1 times y0
现在我将z1写为x0加x1乘以y0
plus y1 minus z0 minus z2.
加y1减z0减z2。
So you're actually computing z0 and z2 first,
所以您实际上是先计算z0和z2，
and then using them to compute z1.
然后使用它们来计算z1。
So someone tell me why this is interesting?
所以有人告诉我为什么这很有趣吗？
And just take it all the way to the complexity of an algorithm.
并将其一直处理到算法的复杂性。
Explain to me why this is interesting
向我解释为什么这很有趣
and why Karatsuba's algorithm has-- I'll give it away--
以及为什么唐津算法有-我会放弃-
a lower complexity than theta n square?
比theta n square低的复杂度？
But tell me what it is.
但是告诉我这是什么。
Someone?
有人吗
Someone other than you.
除了你以外的人。
Someone way at the back.
后面有人。
Yup.
对。
Out there.
在那里。
AUDIENCE: It's n to the log base 2 of 3.
听众：以2为底的对数为n。
PROFESSOR: n raised to--
教授：n提出-
AUDIENCE: Log base 2--
受众：对数基础2--
PROFESSOR: --log base 2 of 3.
教授：-以2为底的对数。
That's exactly right.
没错
And now, why did you get that?
现在，您为什么得到了？
Explain to me how you got there.
向我解释你如何到达那里。
AUDIENCE: If you're using three products--
观众：如果您使用的是三种产品，
PROFESSOR: That's right.
教授：是的。
So first insight is that we're only
所以第一个见识是，我们只是
doing three multiplications here.
在这里做三个乘法。
Additions are easy.
添加很容易。
And we're doing three multiplications as opposed
我们正在做三个乘法
to four.
到四个。
So tell me how that equation changed, of tn.
因此，请告诉我tn的等式是如何变化的。
tn equals--
tn等于-
AUDIENCE: 3 [INAUDIBLE].
观众：3 [听不清]。
PROFESSOR: 3 times t of n over 2 plus theta n
教授：n的t乘以2加theta的3倍
because you're doing three multiplications rather than
因为你在做三个乘法而不是
four.
四。
Multiplications are the complicated operation.
乘法是复杂的运算。
Divisions are even more complicated,
除法更加复杂，
but additions are easy, and you could do those in linear time
但是加法很容易，您可以在线性时间内完成
for n-digit numbers.
用于n位数字。
And so, if you do that and then you go off and you say,
因此，如果您这样做，然后离开，然后说：
well, that tells us that tn equals
好吧，这告诉我们tn等于
theta of n raised to log two of three, which is, by the way,
n的theta升为对数三的对数，顺便说一句，
theta of n raised to 1.58, roughly speaking.
大致来说，n的theta升至1.58。
And I do not want to compute that to arbitrary precision,
而且我不想将其计算为任意精度，
though I could.
虽然可以。
But that goes on and on.
但这还在继续。
Why don't you grab this after you're done.
完成后为什么不抓取这个。
But that just goes on and on.
但这只是持续不断。
1.58 is a rough approximation.
1.58是一个近似值。
That's an irrational number too, assuming
假设这也是一个不合理的数字
you think that irrational numbers exist.
您认为存在非理性数字。
That's an irrational number.
这是一个不合理的数字。
So good, that's really all I had.
太好了，那真的是我所拥有的。
By the way, it's 1.58490625.
顺便说一下，它是1.58490625。
I really should have written that down.
我真的应该把它写下来。
1.58-- in the context of this lecture
1.58-在本讲座中
I think it's important that we get
我认为重要的是
at least a few digits a precision.
精度至少要几位数。
Now you can imagine that you could do it better than this.
现在您可以想象自己可以做得更好。
And it turns out that-- we'll talk a little bit
事实证明，我们会谈一点
about this next time-- But you can imagine breaking this up
关于下一次-但是您可以想象将其分解
into not n over two chunks, but n over three chunks.
不是n超过两个块，而是n超过三个块。
Why don't I just break up x into the top third,
为什么我不把x分成前三位，
the middle third, and then the bottom third,
中间三分之一，然后是底部三分之一，
and then try and see if I can get away
然后试着看看我能否逃脱
with fewer than eight multiplications?
少于八个乘法？
Because the original thing would have
因为原来的东西
taken eight, and if I can do less than eight,
拿了八分，如果我做不到八分，
maybe I can reduce that 1.58 number.
也许我可以减少1.58的数字。
So that's a little bit of a preview
所以这只是预览
for what we'll do next time.
下次我们要做什么。
But what I'd like to do is do a demo.
但是我想做的是一个演示。
And I want you to run that-- it's out there so
我要你运行它-它在那里
blank that out for a second.
一秒钟将其清空。
What I'd like to do is really look at a different problem
我真正想做的是看一个不同的问题
than square root of 2, and show you a demo of code
而不是2的平方根，并向您展示代码演示
that Victor wrote that computes this particular quantity that,
维克多（Victor）撰写的计算该特定数量的数据
you would argue, is irrational, to arbitrary digits.
您会认为，对于任意数字而言，这是不合理的。
Though we'll probably only go up to about a thousand today.
虽然今天我们可能只会增加到一千左右。
And if we just look at-- root 2 is kind of boring, right?
而且，如果我们看一下-根2很无聊，对吗？
It's been around for a while.
已经有一段时间了。
Let's go back and remember high school geometry.
让我们回想起高中的几何图形。
So I think your high school teachers
所以我想你的高中老师
would like this lecture.
想要这个讲座。
Nice little review.
不错的小评论。
So what is that about?
那是什么呢？
That's supposed to be a circle, I think, as you've forgotten.
我认为，这应该是一个圆圈，因为您已经忘记了。
That's supposed to be a circle.
那应该是一个圆圈。
And the circle here is a really big circle.
这里的圆圈是一个很大的圆圈。
It's a trillion units long.
它长一万亿个单位。
I'm into big numbers today, big numbers.
我今天有很多人，很多人。
And the center of the circle is c, c for center.
圆的中心为c，c为中心。
That is what's called a radius, in case you'd forgotten.
如果您忘记了，那就是所谓的半径。
And that's b.
那是b。
And this is also a radius, and that's a.
这也是一个半径，那就是。
And what I'm going to do is I'm going--
我要做的就是-
I want to make a drop a little, I guess, perpendicular down,
我想滴一点，垂直向下，
which is one unit high.
这是一个单位高。
So the way that this is structured
所以这是结构化的方式
is that this is one unit high, this obviously
是这个单位高，这显然
is-- someone tell me what that is, CB.
是-有人告诉我CB是什么。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
听众：[听不清]。
PROFESSOR: Half a trillion.
教授：半万亿。
That's half a trillion.
那是半兆。
And obviously, CA is half a trillion.
显然，CA为五万亿。
And if I call this D, somebody who
如果我叫D，
remembers high school or middle school geometry
记得高中或中学的几何
give me an equation for AD.
给我一个AD方程
And that's definitely worth a cushion.
这绝对值得缓冲。
so what's an equation for AD guys?
那么，广告专家的方程式是什么？
Yeah.
是的
Go ahead.
前进。
AUDIENCE: The radius, half-trillion minus the square
听众：半径，半兆减去平方
root of--
的根源
PROFESSOR: Square root of-- Yeah?
教授：的平方根-是吗？
AUDIENCE: Minus the square root of [INAUDIBLE] square minus 1?
听众：减去[音频不清]的平方根减去1？
PROFESSOR: Perfect, perfect.
教授：完美，完美。
OK good.
好的
So AD equals AC minus CD, and that
所以AD等于AC减去CD，
is going to be half a trillion-- that is 500 billion,
将达到五万亿，即五千亿，
a little bit less than bailout money,
比救助资金少一点
but it's close-- 500 thousand minus square root of 500--
但很接近-50万减去500的平方根
this, when you start squaring this, of course,
当然，当您开始平方时，
is not even real, real big money.
甚至不是真实的，真正的大钱。
But 500 thousand squared minus 1.
但是50万平方减1。
So forget the square root of two.
因此，请忘记两个的平方根。
You can put the screen down.
您可以放下屏幕。
So is it on, the projector?
投影机就这样了吗？
AUDIENCE: It's on, it just needs a [INAUDIBLE].
听众：亮着，只需要[听不清]。
PROFESSOR: OK.
教授：好的。
You can turn that on.
您可以打开它。
AUDIENCE: Rolling.
听众：滚动。
PROFESSOR: So what we're going to do
教授：那么我们要做的是
is, I'm just going to show you the digits
是，我只是要向您展示数字
of this crazy quantity being computed to tens of thousands
这个疯狂的数量被计算成数万
of digits.
的数字。
And you argue that this is it something clearly
你认为这很明显
that isn't a perfect square.
那不是一个完美的正方形。
You took a perfect square, subtracted 1 from it,
您取得了一个完美的正方形，减去了1，
and so you have an irrational quantity
所以你的数量不合理
that is going to go on and on.
这将继续下去。
And let's see what that number-- what it looks like.
让我们看看那个数字-它看起来像什么。
OK?
好？
Get out of the way.
走开。
I hope you can see from the back.
希望您能从后面看到。
AUDIENCE: Oh man, really?
听众：哦，真的吗？
PROFESSOR: Looking pretty good so far, looking pretty good.
教授：到目前为止看起来还不错，看起来还不错。
AUDIENCE: That's crazy.
听众：太疯狂了。
PROFESSOR: Somebody see the numbers somewhere else?
教授：有人在其他地方看到过数字吗？
Have you see these numbers before?
您以前看过这些数字吗？
Like 20 minutes ago, like right in front of you?
就像20分钟前一样，就在您眼前？
OK All right.
好的没问题。
So I think that's a good place to stop.
所以我认为这是个好地方。
If you want an explanation for this
如果您要对此进行解释
I think you can go to section tomorrow.
我想你明天可以去节。
I'm going to use a some attendance tomorrow.
我明天要去参加一些会议。
All right.
好吧。
Happy to answer questions about the rest of the lecture,
很高兴回答有关本讲座其余部分的问题，
and thanks for coming.
并感谢您的光临。